Guide to the Janice Gorn Papers MC.98
New York University Archives
Janice Gorn Papers
1940-1988
New York University Archives
Gorn, Janice L.
MC.98
1.75 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, one half manuscript box, and one flat box.
46 audiocassettes
The Janice Gorn Papers cover the professional life of Janice Gorn, a professor of education at New York University from the 1960s to 1990s. The collection contains correspondence, syllabi, dissertation materials, photographs, and sound recordings of lectures given at NYU during the 1970s.
Biographical Note
Janice Gorn was a professor of Interdisciplinary Studies and Education and an administrator at New York University (NYU) from the 1960s through the 1990s. Gorn received her Ph.D. from NYU in 1958 and worked as a professor at Paterson State College in New Jersey 1959 to 1961. In 1961 she was hired as an assistant professor of education. By 1969 she had been appointed to NYU's School of Education, Health, Nursing, and Arts Professions (SEHNAP) as a professor of Interdisciplinary Studies and the only professor appointed solely to the Interdisciplinary Studies program. In 1978, Gorn won a Great Teacher Award, and she continued to teach until the 1990s, on contemporary education issues.
Gore remained active in the school's dissertation proposal seminar and served on all doctoral dissertation committees. Her writing focused on improving students' writing ability, and she frequently argued for a course on teaching and learning spoken English.
Gorn was also active in NYU administration and served on a number of committees and as an ombudsman.
Separated Material
Photographs previously included in the collection were moved to the University Archives Photograph Collection and organized by subject. These photographs were reintegrated with the original collection in November 2018.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Janice Gorn to the University Archives from 1984 to 1993.
Scope and Content
The Janice Gorn Papers document Gorn's experiences as a professor at New York University (NYU). The papers are almost entirely professional in nature and focus on her academic life. Much of the collection consists of Gorn's correspondence with Walter MacKeller, Adolphe E. Meyer, George Nelson and Geoffrey Bruun. Also included are her course syllabi from 1968 to 1981 as well as a draft of Gorn's book Style guide for the writing of scholarly papers, masters' theses and doctoral dissertations, published in 1971. The collection also contains sound recordings of lectures by others on such topics as in-vitro fertilization and Sigmund Freud, as well as photographs of NYU administrators, faculty, and leading public figures from the 20th century.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series: Series I - Correspondence, Series II - Teaching Materials, Series III - Audio Tapes, and Series IV - Photographs. Materials in the first two series are arranged by correspondent or material type and then chronologically. Series III maintains Gorn's original arrangement. Series IV is arranged alphabetically by last name.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions, except Box 1, Folder 1, which is restricted.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Sound recordings have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact New York University Archives, (212) 998-2646, university-archives@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Correspondence.; Education -- Study and teaching -- United States; Dissertations.; Syllabi.; Meyer, Adolphe E.; Nelson, George, 1908-1986; Bruun, Geoffrey, 1898-1988; MacKeller, Walter; New York University -- Faculty -- Women; New York University. School of Education, Health, Nursing, and Arts Professions
- Series I. Correspondence, 1940-1988; .5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of Gorn's correspondence with Adolph E. Mayer, George Nelson, Geoffrey Bruun, and Walter MacKellar.
  - Walter MacKellar-RESTRICTED, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adolphe E. Mayer, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - George Nelson, 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Walter MacKellar, 1940-1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series II. Teaching and Dissertation Materials, 1962-1981; .5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box
  Series II consists of course syllabi, style guide documents, and dissertation materials.
  - Course Syllabi, Reports, 1974-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Course Syllabi, 1968-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Writing Style Guide, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dissertation Materials, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dissertation Materials, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dissertation Materials, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dissertation Materials, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series III. Audio Recordings, 1969-1981; .5 Linear Feet in one oversize flat box; 46 audiocassettes
  Series III consists of sound recordings by others on education, medical ethics and research, social justice, Sigmund Freud, and the arts.
  - William J. Sweeney III, M.D., "In Vitro Fertilization-Scientific Ethical and Human Considerations", 1979 (Box 3, Cassette 1)
  - William J. Sweeney III, M.D., "The Ethics of Medical Research", 1978 (Box 3, Cassette 2)
  - George Nelson, "Seeing", 1977 (Box 3, Cassette 3)
  - Robert B. McKay, "Resolution of Civil and Criminal Disputes", 1977 (Box 3, Cassette 4)
  - Curtis Williams, "Science and Human Values", 1979 (Box 3, Cassette 5)
  - John P. Spiegel, M.D., 1970 (Box 3, Cassette 6)
  - Anthony Storr, M.D., "Freud and Art", 1976 (Box 3, Cassette 7)
  - William J. Sweeney III, M.D., "Problem-Solving with Microsurgery in Gynecological Patients", 1980 (Box 3, Cassette 8)
  - Robert B. McKay, "The Impact of Law on Education E10.2001", 1980 (Box 3, Cassette 9)
  - Richard A. Cloward, "Deviant Behavior: Beyond Freud & Durkheim I", 1979 (Box 3, Cassette 10)
  - Richard Cloward, "The Urban Crisis & Fiscal & Political Change", 1971 (Box 3, Cassette 11)
  - Robin Winks, "The Joy of the Chase or Sleuthing with Clio", 1979 (Box 3, Cassette 12)
  - John Taras, "Creativity Problem Solving and the Dance", 1981 (Box 3, Cassette 13)
  - Robert McKay, "Adversary Justic and the Public Interest", 1978 (Box 3, Cassette 14)
  - John P. Spiegel, M.D., 1971 (Box 3, Cassette 15)
  - John R. Platt, 1969 (Box 3, Cassette 16)
  - Robert B. McKay, "The Future of Affirmative Action E10.2001", 1979 (Box 3, Cassette 17)
  - Robin Winks, "The Mastery of Detection...", 1980 (Box 3, Cassette 18)
  - John Taras, "Creativity, Problem-Solving, 1981 (Box 3, Cassette 19)
  - Lawrence Cremin, 1970 (Box 3, Cassette 20)
  - Robin Winks, "The Art & Science of Professional Snooping", 1978 (Box 3, Cassette 21)
  - Richard A. Cloward, "Deviant Behavior: Beyond Freud & Durkheim, II", 1979 (Box 3, Cassette 22)
  - Curtis Williams, "The Genesis of an Experiment", 1981 (Box 3, Cassette 23)
  - Curtis Williams, "The Genesis of an Experiment E10.2002", 1980 (Box 3, Cassette 24)
  - John P.Spiegel, M.D. "Theory of Variations in Cultural & Subcultural Values-Conflicts & Adaptations", 1976 (Box 3, Cassette 25)
  - Robert McKay, "Justice and Equality", 1975 (Box 3, Cassette 26)
  - George Nelson, "Visual Illiteracy", 1976 (Box 3, Cassette 27)
  - John P. Spiegel, 1969 (Box 3, Cassette 28)
  - Richard Cloward, "What Did the Poor Get?", 1971 (Box 3, Cassette 29)
  - Frances Fox Piven, 1970 (Box 3, Cassette 30)
  - Curtis Macomber, violin; Robert Dan, viola; March Shuman, cello; E10.2001, 1979 (Box 3, Cassette 31)
  - William J. Sweeney III, M.D. "New Solutions to Gynecological Problems: Microsurgery", 1981 (Box 3, Cassette 32)
  - Curtis Williams, 1975 (Box 3, Cassette 33)
  - Frances Fox Piven, Lecture, 1972 (Box 3, Cassette 34)
  - Anthony Storr, M.D., Lecture, 1971 (Box 3, Cassette 35)
  - Richard A. Cloward, "Theories of Change and Management of Deviant Classes", 1975 (Box 3, Cassette 38)
  - Richard A. Cloward, "Poverty and the Poor", 1972 (Box 3, Cassette 29)
  - Richard A. Cloward, "Relationship Between Relief Crises and Economic Crises", 1969 (Box 3, Cassette 40)
  - Robert McKay, "Impeachment-A Lawyer's View", 1974 (Box 3, Cassette 41)
  - Robert McKay, "Legal Services to the Poor", 1975 (Box 3, Cassette 42)
  - Gates Lecture, "Ecological Principles and the Environment", 1972 (Box 3, Cassette 43)
  - Sawhill, "Technology and Economic Growth", 1976 (Box 3, Cassette 44)
  - Sawhill, "The Future of Democracy", 1975 (Box 3, Cassette 45)
  - Rosenthal, "Diogenes, Pygmalion & the PONS: Deception, Sex and Eavesdropping in Non-verbal Communication", 1978 (Box 3, Cassette 46)
- Series IV. Photographs, 1965-1976; .25 Linear Feet in one half manuscript box
  Series IV consists of photographs of Geoffrey Bruun, Ramsey Clark, Walter MacKellar, Channing E. Phillips, Lewis Thomas, and others.
  - Portraits and snapshots, 1965-1976 (Box 4)